all right welcome back coort 7 we're in
our second discussion on chapter two so
let's head over to
two we can begin with
anyone's thoughts or Reflections or
any question or idea or section of the
text they want to begin with OR
curiosity from to or just some quote
they want to go to
anyone can just raise their hand or type
it in the
chat okay actual go for it sure so one
thing that I found a bit interesting
it's on page 26 of the book um it says
the person can resolve this discrepancy
in two ways it's talking about this
thing of looking at um like expecting to
see an apple when you look and then
actually seeing a frog and it says first
she could change her mind about what
she's seeing so actually that it's a
frog instead of an apple um or she can
fiate the nearest apple tree and see
something that looks very much like an
apple this resolv the initial
discrepancy but in a different way um so
she's kind of doing an action to make
the world fit more her model and they
they do another example afterwards but I
I'm kind of curious about exactly how
this tradeoff is done when would you
choose to do one thing over the other
when would you choose to do an action
versus when would you choose to do a um
like an update of your internal model uh
especially in a situation where you
don't know you know perhaps if you've
had this situation happen many times you
kind of learned that it's important to
know that it's a frog uh so you don't
want to look away you want to up your
model but what if you're meeting it the
first time I was a little bit confused
about
that great question anyone have a
thought on
this you're likely doing both in
parallel much of the time somebody who's
too fixated on one or the other that's
tends to be a neurotic problem or
Worse what that's greate um but there a
few few ways to take
this first there's the secret third
option which is neither discrepancy
doesn't have to be resolved but it is
kind of like the equivalent of a a ball
on a shelf it's like an unresolved
potential energy or like an unburnt
candle it's like an unresolved Gibs free
energy differential however it isn't the
case that a discrepancy is resolved one
of these two ways however these are the
two ways that there can be the reduction
or of discrepancy or or discrepancy
continue to increase so then the
question is like okay in in what ways uh
are or could be discrepancy resolved
through inference and through through
action
um there's defin ways to take this um in
the in the particular partition so
that's splitting up into these four
nodes these two nodes that constitute
the the two directions of the blanket
and then the internal and the external
states that are partitioned off from
each other from that blanket those are
all happening
simultaneously so one answer is they're
both separately in play so you could
have a situation where where neither uh
belief updating nor action updating were
happening like a rock you could have a
situation where both were
concurrently um
updating sometimes it can be helpful to
think about these kind of multiple time
scales of what changing the mind can
look like the fastest time scale which
is kind of equivalent to the forward
pass on a neural network is just the the
forward inference that's just all the
kind of parameters are staying the same
and then new observation comes in basy
and update cranks then at a slightly
slower time scales um corresponding to
attention and learning mechanisms
there's kind of like those are
corresponding to like weight updating in
a neural network and so those those are
like slower kinds of changing the
mind um changing the world through
action also like that's very dependent
on what the kind of action is for
example
here the um eyes were moved so it's a
muscular action to bring the
observations into alignment with the
expectations however there wasn't a
change in the world so visual activity
is kind of a special kind of action
because it doesn't modify the world but
it is still a way to reduce discrepancy
through action so it's kind of a kind of
on the borderline like is that changing
the world me your eye is part of the
world so that is but it it doesn't
modify like any kind of latent
State then there are the actions that
have like a more you know turning on the
air conditioner or the heater that
actually
modify the world so short answer they're
both happening
uncoupled and then when you look at the
specifics of the generative model then
you can you could separately talk about
like the pro cities of a model to update
its beliefs if it has a fixed belief
distribution then it's not going to
update its beliefs if it has a very
broad belief distribution prior then
observations May update its beliefs a
lot and then similarly depending on like
the efficacy and the agency of the
actions that are being discussed then
maybe taking actions to modify you know
changing the temperature in the room if
you have a really fixed physiological
prior on body temperature and the air
conditioner is right there then that's
going to be reflected in the model and
you'll see changing the world if there's
no air conditioner or the agent doesn't
know about it and it's able to like
learn different
physiological um temperatures or has a
very broad temperature range that it
could be okay
in maybe that would be the behavior that
you'd
see here's like the temperature
simply changing one's mind does not seem
very adaptive but acting to lower the
body temperature
is right thanks a lot and I think I was
just interested in about um so that
makes sense to us that it uh that we get
more out of CH trying to actively change
our body temperature than just believing
oh um I actually don't have this body
temperature anymore but where are we
learning that is that through some kind
of trial and error that we're learning
this is this like an evolutionary prior
or where did we get this
from yeah it's a it's a good question so
um when you construct the model then you
get to create whatever the distribution
is then ask you well but how how did
that prior on body temperature come to
be and that the evolutionary account is
um you know in the 98° thermal bacterial
niche
the bacteria that didn't have optimal
growth that didn't expect themselves to
be at that temperature those have been
swept off the table so we end up seeing
a phenotypic
distribution that's the the fitness
distribution of the bacteria in the
thermal vent that corresponds like to a
thermal
gradient
um another another kind of consideration
is actions are being selected also from
a probability distribution like there's
no proposal of some auxilary reward
distribution we're updating our policy
prior habit into the policy posterior
we'll look at that like later in the
chapter so we're doing inference on
action we have inference on perception
those the that's active inference um so
in terms of the belief Distribution on
perceptions that
you can think okay like the beliefs
about the temperature in the room but
also there's the beliefs about turning
on the air conditioner so now which
which um then the the um sort of
liability of both is defined so if the
distribution that one of these if the
Habit distribution is like um 100% I
turn it on 0% heater you know 100% air
conditioner 0% heater then that is like
it's like terministic action selection
versus one that's more spread out across
the action possibilities so you can kind
of get that interpretability when you
see the model and then that's why
there's like when you do specify model
it's like and this comes up in chapter
six you kind of think more structurally
about the
model and then there tends to be a lot
of parameter sweeping and like
investigation across different
combinations like you could try
10 different um kind of widths of Prior
on the perception side from very tight
to very loose and then similarly on the
action side sweep across 10
by1 and then look at um you know color
in each cell by the probability of times
that they turned on the air
conditioner so it's it's not always just
about finding like one kind of specific
parameterization especially with these
more intuition pump models but often
it's more about
sweeping and then looking at like oh um
you know there's kind of a there's a
manifold where on this side this is the
case and on that side this is the
case thanks a lot yeah thank you um any
other question or
chat oh also just to sort of yeah yeah
go ahead
Andrew are you saying this but the space
could potentially be not smooth right if
there are if there are Jagged jumps in
terms of response to different
probabilities does
does I'm not trying to be too technical
but does that make sense it it could be
a a jagged space that has like piecewise
squares or something yeah it could be a
fully discrete space I mean there there
could be a continuous space Also with
with nonlinearities but also it could
just be a fully nonlinear or I mean a
fully discrete space like it could be a
checker game or a chess
game so then that then that
um then those sweeps would have sharp
boundaries okay
look's yeah go ahead oh that just
matches
that it doesn't have to be
nice cuz I was thinking why would you do
parameter sweeping instead of some type
of optimization like but there may not
be a nice you know smooth space to do
optimization
on
so yeah yeah I mean you you've explored
that and know a lot of areas sometimes
when you fully like the fully synthetic
when you fully get to specify it like
we're playing Connect Four so it's a
discrete space there's a discrete action
space there's a discrete game playay
space or
tic-tac-toe then it's like well behaved
and discret but then when you get into
like
discretized forms of systems that have
continuous character
then like then there's all these other
issues that could come
up also just want to make one kind of
General comment just chapters one and 10
are are like book ends it's like
introduction and kind of conclusion and
they're they're similar chapters they
contextualize active inference chapter
four is where we're going to meet the
actual generative model itself the
generative model is kind of like the
transfer station or the midpoint on the
high road and the low road we're in
chapter two so we're talking about model
architecture so these are things that
you can build these are ba go starting
from Bas
equation and using basian statistics to
build up architectures that have a
perception inbound sense making element
and an act
outgoing control theoretic
element the high road is where we'll get
to the free energy principle it's kind
of like imperative for survival and some
of those topics but in the low road it's
kind of like tinkering and cobbling with
different model architectures and
motifs I have a question uhhuh so I'm
from the transitioning from
uh free energy to expected free energy
um I mean I I guess it makes a lot of
sense to to actually take the expected
value of the the free energy but is
there like that derivation wasn't really
that clear to me it was just like here's
the expected free energy do you know
have any good resources or where you can
actually see that
derivation great question well one is in
octopus's math
work um
I I think tomorrow and and continuing
it'll be drawn out um a little bit also
over it you can and you can follow like
click on the little icon for the a
here's equation 2.5 so few few things
about the equation um we have the
screenshot also there's there's the uh
plane
latac this can help if you are putting
it into like a language model and we
have some of these experiments with
interpreting and asking questions about
it not not saying they're all 100% like
complete or anything but in the canvas
for two point and then also for for many
but not all the equations there's
the um natural
language pronunciation basically which
can be helpful and so if it's missing
people people can add it so that that
can
um we we'll have to fix this because it
looks like a lot oh I I kind I know what
happened here
okay there we go so these are the lines
all right in 2.5 there's a few resources
so
um let's
just where do how do we get to 2.5 and
2.6 these are some of the key equations
okay 2.5 equation 2.5 is variational
free energy it these are both vfe and EF
are functionals so there are functions
that have the arguments that are other
functions that the arguments can include
other functions so f is the functional Q
is the variational belief distribution Q
is the distribution that we get to
control the form of so it is set by the
model to have like an analytically
tractable form like a gaussian
approximation so even if the world is
non you know the world's bodal and then
the model saying but but I'm using a
gaussian so that gives me all these like
nice methods then also all the
pathologies like if the world's biotal
and you're fitting a gaussian you could
you know potentially you fit to only one
hump but not the other or you end up
blurring over both the middle so it's
not not not that if you know if there's
a mismatch on form then this will lead
you downhill to not necessarily like the
best of all possible outcomes but given
the selection of the form of Q it will
be the best possible outcome it's a
functional of the belief distribution
and one incoming data point why so
variational free energy is kind of like
this real time check on like how
surprised am I with this data point
variational free energy bounds
surprise minimizing surprise is
equivalent to maximizing model evidence
if you were minimally surprised with the
new temperature readings coming in that
would be equivalent to saying you had
like the maximum likelihood model of the
temperatures coming in you're making the
best possible predictions is equivalent
to saying that you were minimally
surprised so this is bounding minimal
surprise then um it is only dealing with
belief in a moment and one data point
coming in so that's why it's this kind
of like real time sense
making
indicator
2.6 is when we start looking into
talking about observations that haven't
happened yet at the future and action
planning G expected free energy it's
taking in pi which is this policy vector
it sums to one it's a probability
distribution over
actions the policy prior is the Habit
distribution G is going to sharpen that
policy prior into a policy posterior
which then you could sample from like
according to the probabilities or you
could just select the likeliest action
okay how do we get between the different
lines again in this canvas here for 2.5
and 2.6 there's some useful resources um
um here's equation 2.5 walk
through um Ali
ramju Yak smal Jonathan shock have all
done like have have contributed
variously to these sections so that's
one good
PDF
um here I
think this was
yakups the interesting thing for 2.5 and
and this is like again why there's so
many dots to connect with the math is
2.5 actually um it's not
that one you go to two and two you go to
three maybe there's a maybe there's a
way to do that as well but here's the
derivation going from one to two and
then one to
three so these may be some useful
resources
also
here let's see if this resource is still
there Professor Jonathan shock has
written up a sort of math
overview August 12 I don't know if that
renders to the current date just or if
it was like actually edited at this
current date that also has a lot of
information so that's something that
that takes a lot of uh coats of paint I
think but it it it really is there and
grounded and if we can pull out and help
highlight
like all those threads and show okay
here's where this is grounded in the
definition of Shame and entropy or
definition of surprise and likelihood
that'll be
cool one other thing I'll say is um
variational free energy is kind of more
of a classic quantity it's the quantity
that's used in variational inference um
like variational physics variational
Auto encoders and so on whereas expected
free energy is just one choice of a way
to model
futures for example there's also this is
EF expected free energy also there's
free energy of the expected future so
there's several other future oriented
approximators that have been proposed
but variational free energy is kind of
the
classic
Adam yeah like something that I'm
wondering about and I haven't really
quite like understood yet um is that so
from like my my own personal past and
like where I'm coming from up until
active inference I had been reading
quite a bit about like maximum entropy
inference in like John Hart from
Berkeley and Edward Thomas James and uh
even like pier
llas and um trying to think so anyways
definitely like ET James he was really
like a proponent of Max ant inference
and um
prior to active inference I had I had
been thinking about like the stability
of syst systems in the maximum entropy
State and the way
that if if the energy of the of the free
energy equation is is constant then by
the increase of entropy it automatically
minimizes the free the free energy right
so just that the Min the men free energy
is the equivalent
or not necessarily but can be equivalent
to the maximum entropy and
so I don't know if anyone else has been
thinking about this or maybe if if you
like also I don't know any thoughts on
that yeah that's a great question it it
H has not been um fully fully fleshed
out but here's one kind of
recent discussion where it came up and
where they explicit ly highlighted
this okay so here was it it
um okay this is the octave data sampling
paper so
observations um it's kind of this is
kind of like like building on that
discussion of the equation 2.5 VF so
that's where the variational free energy
for data point and a prior are going to
be
described you could also look at a data
point and and your prior and disc like
what was the epistemic value of that
data point coming in how much did we
learn from it um here they're in a
clinical study setting so like the real
Target uncertainty to resolve is about
the efficacy of these different
treatments
um they use max ENT sampling
and then they also compare that with the
expected Information Gain driven
sampling
so there's a very
um okay here we go several examples
would yield identical results had we
adopted data sampling based upon Max
entropy
sampling the key differences emerge when
variance around predicted outcomes is in
homogeneous so when there's
equal variability
profiles like let's just say that we're
we're interested in the temperature
distribution in this room and all of our
sensors have equal VAR sensor
variability then we can sample from the
most the sections that we're least
certain about the
temperature and that's like a Max ENT
sampling
strategy however let's just say that
there was regions in the room that had
different
variability and there were sensors with
different variability so just to kind of
simplify let's just say we had high and
low variability sensors and there's high
and low variability areas in the room so
if we were just going to sample based
upon
variability period measurement
variability like total
variability then maybe this we'd be
ending up sampling from sensors that
were highly variable but regions where
we actually were not not that uncertain
about the temperature at that
location so in the case where the
sensors where the sensor variability we
don't have to worry about then these
approaches are
equivalence but there's actually an
additional level of nuance possible so
it's it's closely aligned with Max and I
think again it would be it would be
great to to draw this out better
but
um it's sampling from a total epistemic
value which is able to kind of
like accommodate that case where there's
variability sensors and the variability
of the temperature parts of the
rim yeah I see that I'll have to look
into that that sounds interesting cool
yeah the the slides are there the and
the paper um and and we we that's an
interesting thing to keep on
exploring what exactly what exactly um
this is just on the website I can get to
this thep yeah um just here's the just
like 57.0 that was the the background
and then 57.1 and point2 um Carl friston
and Thomas Parr
joined I forget which one of the weather
was d one or. two but in one of them
Carl gave a a very vifer defense of
epistemic value because often times
people say Okay epistemic value learning
in service of pragmatic value right like
learning is good for something when it's
pragmatic and he gives a extended
thought on like how they're kind of
like
separate but they're unified under the
expected free energy but um like
epistemic value is its own distinct kind
of value from pragmatic
value whether or not those learnings
contribute to epistemic or I mean
contribute to pragmatic
outcomes I
don't no sorry all over my hand okay
yeah
th this the epistemic um like active
data sampling like on the biological
side it's really interesting because it
describes for example is
secades epistemic driven action
selection but then also they explore
having a cost function so that could be
like how much how much cents does it
cost to make an API
call and then that is the
parameterization question is like how
much epistemic value how many bits of
information are worth one cent of an API
call um or in the case of the clinical
trial there's like you could have a cost
associated with the number of times that
sampling occurs or um cost reflected by
a preference for survival but if the
preference is purely for survival and it
was like some kind of extreme utility
driven clinical trial then a sampling
algorithm would choose to sample nothing
so it' be uninformative with zero
observations however it would have
achieved maximum preference satisfaction
because it wouldn't have observed any
sickness or
death so they talk about a few of these
kind of like interesting
cases and they they build it up very
clearly like how do you add in the cost
and all these different
things and this is like a different
graphical model than comes up in the
textbook again it's the clinical trials
setting but but to connect it with the
textbook
like
these are basing graphical
models and so a lot of the the kind of
structural analysis of a situation comes
down to what are the variables what are
like the observable variables what are
the environmental variables what are the
and there's there's not really like an
agent like kind of sense an action agent
unless you chose to see like the
clinical design team's observations and
decisions in in that light um what are
the observations what are the
environmental variables what are their
influences upon each
other that lays out like the
skeleton and then there's the question
of either generating synthetic data from
that skeleton in that in the forward
direction or explore in chapter n of the
textbook is like how do you go from
observations
to inference on those latent factors
like um what is the efficacy of the
treatment anyone else give like a
thought on chapter 2 or question or a
page or we can look at some of the
questions come on go for
it yeah thanks um yeah I've been
thinking a bit about like the
distinction
between pre energy and expected pre
energy
and sort of thinking about like
so in like in a way aren't all
actions requires planning or like is
there actually a clean distinction in
practice when we when we minimize F and
when we minimize G or is it like a bit
of a fussy line in between and in
practice we're only doing the one or if
you know what I'm getting at
yeah great great question so let let's
go to pmdp documentation that this can
this can um clarify a few of those
things
one uh heris stic is if you're
considering explicit planning so more
than one time Step Ahead like policy
sequences that have a Time Horizon
that's not
one if you want to do explicit planning
Tre search policy roll out um deep
active
inference then you do need to use
expected free energy so if explicit
planning is going to come into play then
you go with expected free energy if it's
just
single time step then it can you you can
just sort of have that reactive
updating um yeah hon let me um that's in
in the
uh
equations equation 2.5
put in the
chat yeah
so if there's explicit planning yes EF
has to come into
play if you have an agent that is not
doing explicit
planning it could do action selection
using vfe so what that would look like
and and is like you have um a belief
Distribution on the temperature in the
room and a belief Distribution on your
habits related to the air condition
conditioner like I'm 50% likely to turn
on the air conditioner or not new
observation comes in it instantaneously
updates the belief distribution that's
the sensemaking element and it
instantaneously updates your um your
policy distribution which is then
sampled from so there's not roll out or
anticipation explicitly of future
unobserved outcomes which is what you
would get with
ef but you only get one time step there
so
um here in in
pmdp it's
um they really especially in the um
documentation make it pretty clear and
declarative like there's only two
actions here but here even for a single
time
step moving left and moving right
they're they are considered with
expected free energies because there's
actually like a question of what what
would I expect to see if I went left and
what would I expect to see if I went
right so that's kind of like you know
there's a lot of way ways to shade that
but that's kind of like the theological
aspect of action is when expected free
energy comes into play which is like
what what would I see if I went left
versus what would I see if I went right
right versus the sort of past pushing
forward without an explicit teeology
would be like I have a 50% chance of
left and right prior on policy I just
saw um a light or a glucose gradient
from the left that just bumped me to
6040 I sample from the 6040 and I go
left but it wasn't based around what
would I see so it wasn't like based
around that what what is the epistemic
value and the pragmatic value
of these two
Alternatives that's the
real policy like planning as
inference versus more of like a
reactive policy just habit unupdated or
updated habit distribution and then just
drawing from that without explicit
consideration of the
consequences and maybe just a short
followup question
um so yeah I guess you can make it like
really clear when when writing a a
program about it but in the context of
of living organisms when you yeah so
like what is what is one time step then
um could maybe
like develop that discussion a bit on
like specific for living organisms
[Music]
um yeah well math territory H how do we
develop continuous Andor discrete time
models maps of complex multiscale
systems like there's not really a
natural time click for a body per se
it's not simply like the heartbeat it's
not the seconds it's not the breath so
then there's a lot of Moder degrees of
freedom with how they
model time
um and then to what extent the modeler
chooses to test here's some models I
made where there's planning happening
and here's some models where planning
isn't
happening that that that's one thought
but but yeah
like does anything plan or when does
planning happen or like one old active
joke was like active inference only
works for one time step
but then you can compress and make that
one time step very
complex so that you like it could be one
mult like one nested time
step that that would subsume what looks
like
planning like if if um let's just say
that we have we were um talking about
like financial decision making or
something like that and we had a a a
policy decision that was being made at
the yearly time
scale if someone only knew about
day-to-day decision making that one time
scale of the yearly model might look
like it had been planned over many
days or there could be a map that just
said we have a single policy we make one
decision per
year but then that model wouldn't be
able to make decisions day by day but it
might look you know it this just gets
into like how I mean how and we can make
many models from the biological
phenomena and then that that's kind of
the interesting question like is there
evidence for planning in is
secades or is it simply
marcovia and we can totally account for
is secades based upon location of the
Gaye at a moment the incoming
observation and the belief distribution
about what would be epistemically
valuable or like is there a
residual that that model can is not
accounting for that is suggestive of
like twostep Cade Planet I don't know
but those are like the kinds of of
research Pathways where where if you are
looking for where is their planning
happening thank you
um
actually sure so uh I'm pretty new to
active inference and I'm kind of trying
to right now get a intuitive feeling for
some of the um equations especially the
one we were looking at before I'm
wondering if we could just talk a little
bit about how the terms kind of relate
to each other and how actually I might
be able to send you uh I just kind of
cooked up something quickly before here
in the chat I kind of tried to create a
visualization of the um I don't know if
you have access to it uh I sent the link
Yeah so basically let's see here yeah so
the idea is that you have like the Q of
X and the P of X and Y and as far as I
understand I might have made some
mistakes but as far as I understand you
minimize the free energy we're looking
at like the top uh version of the
equation right the first line um so we
have the Q ofx which is our belief
distribution is that correct like our
belief of the Hidden States yep then we
have the P of Y and X which is just the
probability of Y and X happening as far
as I understand when P of y and x and q
of X are like exactly the same that
minimizes fre eny is that
correct yeah well great work with this
this is this is super cool and it'd be
awesome to to continue to develop these
like interactive slider based things
which which many people have kind of
like brought up but um yeah like what
variational optimization does is the
modeler has chosen their family of
variational distributions that they're
going to be sliding the well- behaved
knobs on so like we're going to be using
a gaussian again that's not saying the
world is gaussian it's saying the the
modeler is choosing to to do
optimization you know descent with this
G um and then the ball rolling downhill
on that variational free energy
landscape until it rests at the bottom
what is the bottom of that energy well
it's where that observation coming in
given the belief distribution is is the
least surprising possible or it it
bounds surprise now that bound if the
generative process were gaussian and the
generative models gaussian
then you'll get like then it to it bound
surprise and and kisses it if the
generative process were something
different and you were doing a gine
approximation you still would get the
best possible gussian
approximator but then there would be
still like a
constant that that was like surprised
that couldn't be reduced because you
were fitting the best possible Galaxy
but it still was being
um because it was like not the same
family as a generative
process couldn't reduce all the
uncertainty but yeah this is really cool
right like this is just a very quick um
but but I do think it helps to kind of
play around with it and get a feeling
for how things change because one thing
I read in the book was that if you set
the mean of both to zero um you can see
that uh have to add some kind of quick
reset button as well but you can see
that uh as the they say that if you have
little evidence which would mean that
your P of X and Y would be really really
um kind of broad right so if you turn
the the bottom uh all the way up like
the yeah you you turn it up up up up up
then you start getting a free energy
that's higher but then actually as you
they say that you should as far as I
understand it that when you don't have a
lot of evidence you should also be very
uncertain certain so if you I'm seeing
the P of uh X and Y distribution as
being broad as not having a lot of
evidence and then if you take the Q of X
and take the standard deviation up on
that while the uh or sorry the standard
deviation you'll see that if the
standard deviation of the PX and Y is
also very very broad it does
minimize uh variational free energy as
well does that uh make sense with what
what the truth is
or yeah like I'm I'm really interested
in this um change from a
uh single
well to potentially I mean potentially
some
plateau and then here potentially like a
symmetry break where if the first
observation coming in were here
maybe it breaks to the right and then
continues to follow the gradient and
down to here and then a future
observation couldn't even if it came
from here it'd be like okay now back to
here and back so then it's like trapped
in an energy well so it's like what are
these situations where even when we have
a gaan prior and a gaussian generative
process like what is happening where
we're we're getting a more like a um
quartic like kind of two energy
well free energy distribution so I'm not
sure if I'm illustrating it in the wrong
way and maybe uh like the blue graph is
basically Q ofx uh times the natural
logarithm of P of Y and X before it gets
kind of summed up into the so that's
kind of what that's showing I don't know
if that was the same thing you were
referring to but just so you
know yeah cool maybe octopus and others
can can play with it and keep keep on
developing it or um or post the the repo
that it comes from but this looks cool
um so just one quick followup so earlier
in the beginning you were talking about
I mean can I understand it in that way
that when you're very certain because
they say in the book that if you are if
you have little evidence then you should
also not be so certain in your model um
and I'm wondering whether that
uncertainty is characterized by having a
very broad Goa for example and whether
the lack of evidence is also uh kind
of how do you say represented by having
a very broad gion if you're using a
go
yes this kind of relates like you have
to the standard
deviation um what comes up later is this
like learning by counting so let's just
say we've observed one heads and one
Tails we might have um a distribution
belief what is the probability of this
coin coming up heads it's centered at
0.5 but it might be very broad whereas
if we had one million heads and one
million Tails observed then we would
have very sharp Gan around
0.5 so there's different ways to kind of
implement that but but broadly when
you're less confident when there's more
epistemic value on the
table then belief distributions come to
look like
uniformity and then as you gain
Precision it gets more of a central
tendency and then the extreme case is
basically a dir
Delta function so it's just a spike at
one
location that might not even be
learnable and then it's just like it's
here and even if you got even if you
have a spike at 0. five and you it just
then it doesn't matter what you observe
because there's no probability Mass on
outside of that one Spike so it's like
those observations are are like
discarded whereas the uniform
prior um is which is kind of like the
frequentist case
interestingly is like the the I mean
it's the
least bias in terms of its
sensitivity but then then you realize oh
but then the but the updating is the
bias that is statistical
bias right cool thanks a lot and if
anyone else is interested in like
building these kind of tools or
something please reach out to me because
I think it' be pretty nice to have some
more visualizations of how these things
play
together so but thanks a lot for the
explanation cool yeah it'd be so fun
like for each equation just like even to
like we you could have like natural
language and
translations pseudo
code some different languages some
interactables like there's what are the
kind of like different
forms that that we could interact with
and then also
like where and when and how like in
theory and in the specific
implementations you know the dozens of
implementations like where did the
modelers choose to use the energy minus
entropy kind of statistical
mechanics decomposition of f where did
they use a complexity minus
accuracy kind of Statistics basing
information Criterion type and then
where is there like a Divergence minus
evidence
like if they're
equivalent then does it matter or like
are one of these more computationally
intensive to compute or is there like is
there a reason or a setting why one of
these decompositions on F is better and
then that really gets opened up in the
policy selection for expected free
energy like we talk the most about
epistemic plus pragmatic value that's a
very interesting decomposition for for
policy
selection but it's equivalent to these
two ambiguity plus
risk kind of classic control theory
esque um investing type
decompositions and then both of these
are equivalent to the again energy minus
entropy but then it's like but then are
we even talking about planning if we're
talking about energy minus entropy or
how how and then
like what if we had like a vent diagram
it's like here's the total
amounts and here's the the variance
that's getting partitioned into
epistemic here's the variance that's
getting partitioned into pragmatic now I
don't think the
same this I don't think the same
variance is going to ambiguity and risk
nor to energy entropy because the terms
are not equivalent to epistemic plus
pragmatic value so it's like so what
loads on pragmatic value then does that
get
does that get you know loaded onto risk
or onto
ambiguity does pragmatic value get
loaded onto entropy or onto
energy again is there a reason or how
did different modelers do
it the top line for G is is the most
common and the top line for for f is the
most
common I don't know though but those are
like they're they're given as a first
line because they're kind of like the
classic form but it's it's an
interesting topic the rule of four or
more
octopus yeah what is the
rule the rule of four is an idea from
teaching math that developed in the 90s
that was like every concept you look at
you try to have at least four different
representations usually they're verbal
numeric symbolic and um verbal numeric
symbolic and visual and uh what what you
were saying about like we have all these
different representations and we could
add more was just echoed that for
me
cool yeah and here we have we have
there's we have different words in Lang
different natural languages different
graphical um symb it could include
executable
code and then there could be some some
wild cards games and stuff like
that but yeah it always pops up it
seems it be I mean for each of the
equations we could have a column for
like
these and then that creates like you
know if there's 50
equations then it's just like we can
just say okay here's the empty cells
let's try to get something into each of
these cells
CS yeah
that's I'll just delete this because
SE
um yeah I mean this is cool and these
are great questions that's what chapter
2 again we haven't even gotten to active
inference this is saying okay op um Bas
optimality
probabilistic probab probably
approximate basee like pack um uh
probably approximately
correct here's the par partition
splitting systems into these four nodes
minimum of four that's another rule of
four or more kind of splitting into four
two blanket States internal and
external getting into what's basically a
variational auto encoder here it is is
framed in the Sens making
setting and then extending that
variational autoencoder into the
decision- making
setting showing that that expected free
energy unified objective or or
imperative or kind of like loss function
a lot in common with with loss functions
that the special cases of expected free
energy fall out as other
well-known pis stics like if you only
consider pragmatic value you get
expected utility Theory no epistemic
value nothing to learn special case of G
expected
utility in contrast if all outcomes are
equally preferable so there's no
pragmatic value on the table then
epistemic
value yields
Infomax so it's kind of like
saying if you're going to compose with
these basy in
Legos either in the the real time
inference and then also extending out
into the the planning and the action
selection like anything any any any
brick structures you build on the low
road are going to you're going to be
able to approximate them with
variational basian
inference chapter 3 is going to come in
with with more of this phys
flow based
model and and say and um for the
organism like observing itself or for
some for you observing something
else something will act as if it is
bounding its surprise about something
else so low roads like saying anything
you build you're going to be able to
approximate it do variational inference
with that surprise
bounding and then here is more of the
the physics saying and you can model
things such that it that it looks like
that's what they're
doing and then in
four that's where the generative models
actually get
shown and it's like this is this was
built up on the low road and it's kind
of compatible from the high road and
that's why it's placed at the
middle it's just that also four has like
again some more mathematical
background like Jensen's inequality and
properties
logarithms um variables and their
dependencies in graphical
models but then figure 4.3 does bring us
to the disree and the continuous time
generative models
so that's why it's always just kind of
like like many codes of paint like just
kind of reading through because there's
not really just one order especially as
everyone's going to have different like
questions about different parts um so
that's kind of fun like what are the
more the more pure background
materials like putting this as figure
4.1 might make it seem like this is
like finally we got to act in it's
figure 4.1 it's like well no maybe that
that's just a generic property of
logarithms cool um
well so uh next week for
S we uh it'll be
later
or join at this time next week and uh
either Andrew or I
will revisit applying active again
there's no there's no specific order so
that that can be helpful like chapter 7
goes into essentially the top half of
figure 4.3 so may be useful to to see it
and um we can go into
pmdp python based very imperative pseudo
code like form uh format for the
programming like get the observation
update this do that calculate this do
that um or we could explore a little bit
towards RX and fur which has this
declarative style where it's more like
you declare the base
graph full stop then you declare a kind
of like logistical scheduling of how how
do you update different parts of it so
that has there's a few more steps that
are possibly initially
unintuitive but then in operation it
gives the RX infer style of declarative
programming a lot more performance and
flexibility
okay cool any I mean any with anything
else in the times between just make make
the notes on the chapter Pages or just
prepare them
however oh I'll copy and Dave's on
note ruer four in toolic linguistics
they don't write abstracts like they
used
to okay thank you see you all later bye